Livonia, Mich. Pilgrim United Church of Christ records, 1913-1980.
Congregational Library & Archives
Livonia, Mich. Pilgrim United Church of Christ records, 1913-1980.
RG5544
Congregational Library & Archives
0.85 Cubic Feet
(3 boxes)
The Brewster Congregational Church in Detroit, Michigan, was gathered in 1894. It merged with the Pilgrim Congregational Church in 1924 to form the Brewster Pilgrim Congregational Church. The church moved to Livonia, Michigan, in 1957 and reformed as the Pilgrim Congregational Church. By 1969, the church was renamed to Pilgrim United Church of Christ. The church dissolved in 1979. This collection contains, primarily, vital records, such a membership records, marriage records, and baptismal records, as well as a smaller amount of administrative records.
Pilgrim United Church of Christ (Livonia, Mich.)
Brewster Congregational Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Brewster Pilgrim Congregational Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Evangelical and Reformed Historical Society in March 2021; accession 2021-04.
The contents of the "Ministerial search documents, 1958" folder were originally found in the Detroit, MI: Brewster Congregational Church. (1907) local church history file (17.11.1 D48.5 B7) and transfered to the archives in April, 2025.
Historical Note
The Brewster Congregational Church in Detroit, Michigan, was gathered in 1894. In 1924, the Brewster Congregational Church merged with the Pilgrim Congregational Church, gathered in 1915, to form the Brewster Pilgrim Congregational Church. In 1957, the Brewster Pilgrim Congregational Church partnered with the Mount Hope Congregational Church, gathered 1889, to form the Pilgrim Congregational Church of Greater Detroit. This combined entity sold the Brewster Pilgrim Congregational Church building in 1957 and purchased a new building in Livonia, Michigan, which became the home of the newly reformed Pilgrim Congregational Church.
The exact relationship between Mount Hope Congregational Church and the Pilgrim Congregational Church after 1958 is unclear; the churches seem to have operated independently after this point. The Mount Hope Congregational Church moved to Livonia in 1964 and continues to serve the community today. The Pilgrim Congregational Church joined the United Church of Christ and between 1967 and 1969, the church was renamed to Pilgrim United Church of Christ. In 1969, the church federated with the Livonia Christian Church (Disciples of Christ). The Pilgrim United Church of Christ dissolved in 1979; in 1980 the church building was sold to the Livonia Christian Church.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the records of the Pilgrim United Church of Christ, Livonia, Michigan, and its various predecessor churches. The majority of this collection is vital records, such as Baptismal records, Marriage records, and membership records. The collection also contains some administrative records, including meeting minutes, correspondence, and legal records.
Arrangement
Materials in this collection have been arranged into the three series listed below. Materials within each series have been arranged in chronological order by start date.
Series 1: Brewster Congregational Church records, 1913-1925
Series 2: Brewster Pilgrim Congregational Church records, 1922-1957
Series 3: Pilgrim United Church of Christ records, 1956-1980
Baptismal records.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Marriage records.; Brewster Congregational Church (Detroit, Mich.); Brewster Pilgrim Congregational Church (Detroit, Mich.); Detroit (Mich.) -- Church history.; Livonia (Mich.) -- Church history.; Mount Hope Congregational Church (Livonia, Mich.); Pilgrim United Church of Christ (Livonia, Mich.)
- Brewster Congregational Church records, 1913 1925; 1913-1925; 1 Volume; 2 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains vital records related to the Brewster Congregational Church. The series includes marriage records, baptismal records, and membership records.
  - Church register, 1913 1924; 1913-1924 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Marriage register, 1922 1925; 1922-1925 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Baptismal records, 1922 1925; 1922-1925 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Brewster Pilgrim Congregational Church records, 1922 1957; 1922-1957; 8 Folders
  This series contains vital records related to the Brewster Pilgrim Congregational Church. The series includes baptismal records, marriage records, membership records, a memorial scrapbook, and a church magazine.
  - Baptismal records, 1922 1936; 1922-1936 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Memorial scrapbook, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Marriage register, 1926 1938; 1926-1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Baptismal records, 1932 1939; 1932-1939 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Baptismal records, 1936 1952; 1936-1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Brewster Pilgrim Messenger magazine, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Membership transfers, 1953 1957; 1953-1957 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Dismissions, 1954 1956; 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Pilgrim United Church of Christ records, 1956 1980; 1956-1980; 1 Volume; 8 Folders
  This series contains records related to the Pilgrim United Church of Christ, which had previously been known as the Pilgrim Congregational Church and formed out of the Brewster-Pilgrim Congregational Church. The Series contains membership records, church records and communications, clippings, and directories.
  - Dismissions, 1956 1970; 1956-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Membership records, 1957 1967; 1957-1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Ministerial search documents, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    This folder contains a document titled "The Story of Pilgrim Congregational Church of Greater Detroit" and filled questionnaire from the Congregational board of Pastoral Supply.
  - Church records, 1958 1980; 1958-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Church register, 1960 1965; 1960-1965 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Membership records, 1960 1978; 1960-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1961 1970; 1961-1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pilgrim Progress newsletter, 1962 1978; 1962-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Directories, 1963 1977; 1963-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)